Alexander Ortega

Data Scientist / Data Analyst

Cali, Colombia (UTC-5) (+57) 3163267456 alexandergribenchenko@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexandergribenchenko https://github.com/alexandergribenchenko

Data Scientists with +3 years of experience collecting, analyzing, interpreting and performing data management tasks. Specific experience in evaluation, automation, development and deployment of analytical models. Knowledge in Big Data tools/solutions for advanced analytics and machine learning processes in the cloud. Knowledge on visualization and reporting tools. Communicative skills, problem-solving driven, and critical thinking.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, SQL, Matlab. **Databases:** PostgreSQL, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server.

Data Science Libraries: Pandas, Numpy, SciPy, SciKit-Learn, XGBoost, Pulp, MatplotLib, Seaborn, Plotly, NLTK, SpaCy, Pulp,

TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, PyCaret.

Reporting and Visualization: Power BI, Tableau, Looker.

Cloud services: Azure (Datafactory, Datalake, Databricks, Machine Learning), AWS (RDS, S3, EC2, SageMaker), GCP(BigQuery).

Big data: PySpark, Databricks, Apache Spark ML.

Orquestation: Airflow.

Quality Assurance (Unit Testing): Pytest.

Version Control: Git, Github.

Agile (Frameworks/Tools): Scrum, Kanban, Azure DevOps.

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist, TCS - Tata Consultancy Services, May 2021 - Present

Evaluation, automation, development and deployment of analytical models for the areas of operations planning and digital marketing associated with the aeronautical industry. Translation of the needs of different business areas to analytical solutions that allow obtaining quantitative and qualitative business insights and improve decision-making.

- Classification models: Developed machine learning models to predict airport delays and forecast email marketing open rates, improving operational planning and marketing strategy for the aeronautical industry.
- Regression models: Built models to estimate market size and predict call center volume, enabling data-driven decision-making for business planning.
- Segmentation models: Utilized RFM (Recency, Frequency, Monetary) analysis to segment customers and improve customer targeting and retention for the aeronautical industry.
- Recommendation models: Developed recommendation models for campaign targeting and cross-selling ancillary products, driving revenue growth for the aeronautical industry.
- Optimization models: Created fleet assignment models to optimize aircraft allocation and maximize revenue for the aeronautical industry.
- NLP models: Developed NLP models to analyze customer feedback and improve the overall customer experience for the aeronautical industry.

Tech Stack: Python, SQL, Spark, Pyspark, Azure (Datalake, Databricks, Datafactory, Machine Learning, DevOps), Power BI, Git, Pytest, Docker, FastAPI.

Data Analyst, City Hall of Cali, Administrative Department of Environmental Management— May 2016 - Jun 2020

- Developed and implemented a methodology for analyzing and evaluating real-time environmental noise data in Santiago de Cali, utilizing IoT sensors and streaming data on AWS.
- Generate monthly reports on environmental noise evaluations using Python and SQL. Created a dynamic dashboard
 using Power BI for the city's environmental authority, providing critical insights to inform sound policy decisions
 aimed at addressing environmental concerns. These reports and dashboard were published as a key component of
 the authority's environmental quality bulletins.

Tech Stack: Python, SQL, AWS (Sagemaker, S3, EC2), Git, Github, PowerBI.

Alexander Ortega

Data Scientist / Data Analyst

Cali, Colombia (UTC-5) (+57) 3163267456 alexandergribenchenko@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexandergribenchenko https://github.com/alexandergribenchenko

PROJECTS

Correlation One -Aug 2020 - Nov 2020

- Developed ClassiCode, a data science classification tool based on neural networks and NLP that make the state contracting processes for national government agencies more effective and efficient.
- ClassiCode was the winner among more than 107 projects presented throughout Colombia receiving a \$5,000 USD scholarship, as part of the Data Science For All DS4A Colombia 2020 V3.0 program.

LANGUAGES

English: Upper intermediate (B2). **Portuguese:** Intermediate (B1).

Spanish: Native.

EDUCATION

Universidad Austral de Chile – Valdivia, Chile. *Master of Science, Acoustics and Vibrations,* Dec 2011. **Universidad del Valle** – Cali, Colombia. *Bachelor of Science, Physics*, Dec 2010.

CERTIFICATIONS

Complete Spark Course with Databricks (Big Data) - Coursera. 2021.

Data Science (7 months Bootcamp) – Acámica. 2021.

Data Science For All (DS4A/ Colombia 3.0) (12 weeks Bootcamp) - Correlation One. 2020.

Databases and SQL for Data Science with Python - Coursera. 2020.

Python for Data Science, AI & Development - Coursera. 2020.